so one way of speeding up hit times is
to overlap one hit with another
and we can achieve this for example
through pipelining the cache if the
cache takes multiple cycles to access we
can have a situation where an axis come
in cycle n and it's a hit and now if
another axis comes in cycle n plus one
and it would be a hit tool
in a non-pipeline cache this second
access has to wait until the first
access is done using the cache and it
takes multiple cycles to do that so in
this situation the hit time as seen by
each access is the actual hit time of a
cache
plus the wait time
that the access suffers because it
cannot access the cache until the
previous one is done and in that
situation pipelining the cache so that
we can send in accesses one after the
other will improve the overall hit time
now it may sound straightforward how to
pipeline the cache you just divide it in
let's say three stages but how do you
split
what amounts to basically a read from a
large array because that's really what
the cache is
remember that the cache access consists
of using the index part of the address
to find the set
reading out the tags and valid bits that
correspond to the blocks in that set
comparing the tags and checking the
valid bits for each of these to see
whether it has a hit
combining these
so that we know whether we have an
overall hit
and where in our set once we know where
we read out the data and use the offset
to choose the right part of the large
cache block at which point we have the
data that the processor wants and our
cache access is done so one example of a
cache pipeline would be to have this
part
reading out the tags and so on from the
cache array be stage one
determining the hits
and beginning the data read would be
stage two and finishing the actual data
read all the way to getting the data
would be stage three so as you can see
we can pipeline the cache access
even if we don't know how to actually
break down
the reading from the cache array
especially if the tags and the valid
bits are read before we determine the
hit and we only read the data part of
the cache after we determine the hit in
that case just those two can be separate
stages usually the actual cache hit time
for level one caches will be one two or
three cycles
one cycle caches don't need pipelining
and two and three cycle caches can be
relatively easily pipelined into two or
three stages so usually level one caches
will be pipelined